rainforest-alliance.org 2019-05-07

# Privacy Policy | Rainforest Alliance

### Introduction

The Rainforest Alliance places a high priority on protecting your privacy.

This privacy policy (the “Privacy Policy”) describes how we handle the personal information we collect and process. The Privacy Policy applies to the services that we provide, as well as your use of our websites, mobile apps, other online services and anything else that links to or refers to the Privacy Policy (our “Services”).

### Information We Collect and Receive

We collect and receive information about you in a few different ways:

Information you give us. You can give us information directly. For example:

**Online users**

  * When you contact us, for instance by email or filling out a form on our website, you may give us information such as your name, telephone number, email address, physical address, and other demographic information;
  * When you donate funds online, you give us your billing information, which may include your credit card data; or
  * When you otherwise contact us, for instance through social media.

**Donors**

  * When you send us a check or make a donation by phone, we keep a record of the donation; or
  * When you meet with us in person at events or meetings, we may collect or process information about you for fundraising purposes.

**Farmers and certification clients**

  * Participants in the Rainforest Alliance Sustainable Agriculture Standard certification scheme, the UTZ Certification program, other certification programs or assurance programs, provide data to us through the auditing or review process, either directly or through a certification body, through our traceability tools, including Marketplace, and through the trademark or label approval process.

**Others who contract or partner with us**

  * When you contract with us, receive a grant from us, make a grant to us or participate in trainings.

**Information we process about you may include the following list of data elements:**

  * _Contact details including_ : your name; home and business addresses; email addresses; phone numbers; facsimile number; instant messaging contact; or any other details contained in a signature.
  * _Education and professional qualifications and professional and employment information including_ : degrees and schooling information; licenses and professional memberships; occupation or title; and service fees or other compensation.
  * _Payment processing related information including_ : bank account number; taxpayer identification number or social security number; digitized or electronic signature; location; and credit card information.
  * _Personal characteristics including_ : age; date of birth; gender; marital status; nationality; leisure and interests; and photographs, videos and audio recordings.
  * _Other information_ : In addition to the above, we may collect further information for specific purposes. If we apply for a visa on your behalf we may collect passport information. If you make a large donation to us, we may conduct a criminal or background check for due diligence purposes. We may collect information about consumer products purchased in relation to our special events. We may collect income or salary information for special events and fundraising purposes or for purposes related to research and evaluation of our programs. When we publish editorial content about or conduct research and evaluation on our programs we may collect information about an individual’s economic, familial, cultural or social identity.

**Information we collect or receive when you use our online services**. We also collect or receive information when you use our online Services. We may collect some of this information using cookies, web beacons, and other technologies. When you visit our website, you will receive a one-time cookie pop up consent wherein you are given the opportunity to consent to the use of cookies. Should you decide not to consent to the use of cookies, some functionality and Services related to your use of our websites, applications, or other online services may not work properly.

When you use our websites, we may collect information, including your Internet Protocol (“IP”) address (the unique address of your computer which makes it possible to recognize your computer), type of browser, domain names, time of access and the pages that you visit.

Should you consent to the use of cookies, depending on how you access and use our Services, we may receive:

  * _Log information_. This is information that is automatically collected and stored when you use our Services or the websites and apps of our business partners and affiliates. It may include, for example: 
    * Information about your interactions with the websites, apps, and other services you use, the content you view, the search queries you submit, and information in cookies and similar technologies; and
    * Information about how you access those websites, apps, and other services, your browser or operating system, your IP address, and the website you visited before visiting our Services.
  * _Device information_. This is information we automatically collect and store about the device you use when you access our Services. Device information includes, for example, the type of device that you are using, and certain device identifiers which may be unique to your device.
  * _Location information_. This information can include, for example, information about your location derived from your IP address if you are on a computer, or your mobile device's more precise geolocation information.

Most web browsers accept cookies automatically, but can be configured not to do so or to notify the user when a cookie is sent. If you wish to disable cookies, please refer to your browser’s help section. Please note that you may need to take additional steps beyond changing your browser settings to refuse or disable cookies and similar technologies.

Read our comprehensive Cookie Policy.

**Google Analytics**. We also collect information via Google Analytics. The analytics features we have implemented are Google Analytics Demographics and Interest Reporting, Remarketing, and Google Display Network Impression Reporting. Visitors can opt-out of Google Analytics using the [Ads Settings](https://www.google.com/settings/ads) and by using the [Google Analytics Opt-out Browser Add-on](https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout/).

**Other information**. We may receive additional information about you that is publicly or commercially available and combine that with the information we have collected or received about you in other ways. Also, we receive information about you when you choose to connect with social networking services while using our Services.

### How We Use the Information We Collect and Receive

We use the information we collect and receive for the following purposes:

  * Processing the information is necessary for the performance of a contract to which you are a party or in order to take steps at your request prior to entering into a contract, or
  * The processing is necessary for the purposes of a legitimate interest, or
  * Processing is necessary for compliance with a legal obligation, or
  * You have given consent to the processing of your personal data for one or more specific purposes.

More specifically, we collect and receive information for the following purposes:

**To provide our Services and to enforce any applicable terms of service**. We use the information we collect and receive to provide you with the Services you use or request, and as needed in order to enter into or perform terms of service.

**To provide additional information about Rainforest Alliance’s work**. This information includes updates on projects, new website features, invitations to special events, and opportunities to contribute financially. You will have a possibility to opt out any time you receive this type of information from us.

**To improve our Services**. We also use the information we collect and receive to provide content you or other users are likely to find relevant and engaging. We also use the information to conduct surveys to measure your satisfaction with our Services, which we use to improve our Services. Information collected will allow us to adjust and improve our websites to your wishes and needs and to be able to prepare anonymized statistics about the use of our websites. Using the information to improve our Services is in our legitimate interest.

**To provide effective advertising**. You may receive advertising on third-party websites and apps such as Google AdWords, Facebook, and Instagram. We use the information we collect and receive to advertise and to make the advertising we provide more effective, which is in our legitimate interest. Some of the ways we do this are:

  * Showing you ads based on your online activities, such as your geographic location, the languages you speak, the keywords that you use on search engines, and the types of social media content that you “like” and/or follow, and website content you view;
  * Limiting the number of times you see the same ad; and
  * Measuring the effectiveness of the ads you see.

### How We Share the Information We Collect and Receive

**Third Parties**. We may share certain information we collect or receive with third parties to provide products and services you have requested, when we have your consent, or as described in this Privacy Policy.

We may share information with:

  * _Affiliates_. The information one Rainforest Alliance affiliate receives can be shared among other Rainforest Alliance affiliates.
  * _Business partners_. We may share information with select business partners, who may use the information, (including to provide you with relevant advertising in the U.S.) or to collect and make payments for services, donations or royalties and to confirm audit data.
  * _Other parties_ in response to legal process or when necessary to protect our Services. We may disclose your information to other parties when we have a good faith belief that: 
    * It is necessary to respond to lawful governmental requests or legal processes (for example, a court order, search warrant, or subpoena);
    * The information is relevant to a crime that has been or is being committed;
    * An emergency exists that poses a threat to your safety or the safety of another person; or
    * It is necessary to protect the rights or property of the Rainforest Alliance.

In the event that the ownership of the Rainforest Alliance or an affiliate or their assets changes as a result of a merger, acquisition, sale of assets, or in the unlikely event of a bankruptcy, your information may be transferred to another company.

**Online Training Platforms**. All information collected or received by the Rainforest Alliance’s online training platforms is used to measure the impact of the platforms. To that end, Rainforest Alliance will provide information such as the level of completion of courses and grades earned to the participants and, in some cases, their employer. In addition, the Rainforest Alliance may share de-identified, aggregate information on the performance of participants and the impact of the online training platforms with Rainforest Alliance affiliates and business partners.

**Individual Donors**. From time to time, we do make the street addresses of individuals who reside in the United States and who donate to the Rainforest Alliance available to other not-for-profit organizations whose missions we think might also be of interest to the individual. This applies to donors who give online, through the mail, or by phone. If you do not want us to share your street address with other organizations, please let us know by calling us at the number provided below; emailing us at the email address provided below, or writing to us at the street address provided below.

**Companies or Individuals that Provide Services to the Rainforest Alliance**. Companies or individuals that provide Services to the Rainforest Alliance or act on our behalf may have access to information about you. These companies are limited in their ability to use information they receive in the course of providing Service to us for any purposes other than the services for which we have engaged them.

**Third Parties that Provide Content, Advertising Services, or Functionality on Our Online Services**. Some of the content, advertising, and functionality on our Services may be provided by third parties that are not affiliated with us. Such third parties include:

  * Advertising providers, which help us and our advertising customers provide ads that are tailored to users' interests and understand how users respond to those ads; and
  * Audience-measurement companies, which help us measure the overall usage of our Services and compare that usage to other online services.

Some of these companies may participate in industry-developed programs designed to provide consumers with choices about whether to receive targeted ads. To learn more, please visit the websites of the [Network Advertising Initiative](http://www.networkadvertising.org/) and the [Digital Advertising Alliance](http://www.aboutads.info/choices/).

### Final remarks

**Our Commitment to Security**

We shall provide appropriate technical and organizational measures to protect your personal data against loss or against any form of unlawful processing and shall impose such security obligations on any data processor we shall enlist. For example, we, or our data processor(s), shall use servers that have been placed in a controlled, secure environment, protected against unauthorized access.

**Children's Privacy**

Our Services are intended for a general audience. We do not knowingly collect, use, or disclose personal information from children under the age of 16 without prior parental consent, except as permitted by the Children's Online Privacy Protection Act. If you are a parent who consents to the collection of personal information from your child, you agree that your child may use all of our Services and that we may collect, use, and disclose your child's personal information consistent with this Privacy Policy.

**Records Retention**

Rainforest Alliance keeps records only for as long as they are needed for us to conduct our business and to comply with our legal obligations. We adhere to our Records Retention and Management Policy to determine which records shall be retained and for how long. A copy of our Records Retention and Management Policy can be obtained by contacting [Dirk Straathof](mailto:dirk.straathof@utz.org) or [Molly Stark](mailto:mstark@ra.org).

**European Union (EU) Users**

**Cross-Border Data Transfers**. For data subjects whose data was collected in the European Economic Area (EEA), be advised that we may transfer your information to third countries outside of the EEA, which the European Commission (EC) may not have deemed “adequate” for information security purposes, including the United States. That data is transferred under adequate data transfer mechanisms, including the Model Clauses, which were approved by the EC. You can request a copy of the data transfer mechanisms by contacting Dirk Straathof at dirk.straathof@utz.org or Molly Stark at mstark@ra.org. If your data was collected or processed within the European Economic Area (EEA), you have the following rights, subject to exceptions or requirements under current laws, including the European Union (EU) General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR):

  * The right to withdraw consent to our processing of your personal data at any time
  * Receive a copy of or access to your personal data
  * Request a copy of your personal data to be sent to a third party
  * Restrict processing of your personal data
  * Rectify or correct your personal data
  * Ask us to erase your personal data or delete it

To exercise the rights outlined above, you can contact us at the physical address and/or email provided below. We will respond within one month by: 1) complying with your request as soon as practicable; or 2) providing to you an explanation regarding our inability to comply with your request based on our legal obligations. If your request is complex, we may extend this period by an additional two months, and you will be informed about any such extension within the initial one-month period.

If you withdraw your consent, we will discontinue the processing of your information upon receipt of your withdrawal. However, any processing performed prior to your withdrawal remains a legitimate processing based on a valid consent at the time. We will not be under the obligation to reverse the processing.

Dirk Straathof  
De Ruyterkade 6  
1013 AA  
Amsterdam  
THE NETHERLANDS  
Tel: +31 20 530 8000  
Fax : +31 20 530 8099

Furthermore, you have the right to lodge a complaint with an EU supervisory authority should you feel that we have violated any of your rights as provided under the GDPR.

**How to Contact Us**

If you have questions or concerns about this Privacy Policy or about Rainforest Alliance's privacy practices in general, please contact us at:

Rainforest Alliance  
233 Broadway, 28th Floor  
New York, NY 10279  
(888) MY-EARTH  
+1 (212) 677-1900  

**Changes to This Privacy Policy and Additional Information**

We may update this Privacy Policy from time to time, and so you should review it periodically. If there are significant changes to Rainforest Alliance's information practices, you will be provided with appropriate online notice.
